<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Xiaowei Zhang on Xiaowei Zhang</title>
    <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Xiaowei Zhang on Xiaowei Zhang</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Ranking and Selection: High-dimensional Covariates and General Dependence</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/rshc_wsc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 19:05:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/rshc_wsc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Stochastic Kriging for Queueing Simulation with Stylized Models</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/sesk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/sesk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Scalable Approach to Enhancing Stochastic Kriging with Gradients</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/scalablegesk_wsc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/scalablegesk_wsc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting Overdispersed Arrivals via Bayesian Simulation</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/bayesforecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/bayesforecast/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge Gradient for Robust Selection of the Best</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/robustkg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/robustkg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Affine Jump-Diffusions: Stochastic Stability and Limit Theorems</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/ajd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 17:48:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/ajd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation Scaling in Large Service Systems: Statistics, Stochastics, and Simulation</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/talk/thu-sem_18/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/talk/thu-sem_18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Embed your slides or video here using [shortcodes](https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/). Further details can easily be added using *Markdown* and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code. --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ranking and Selection with Covariates: Simulation for Personalized Decision Making</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/talk/thu-ie_18/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/talk/thu-ie_18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Embed your slides or video here using [shortcodes](https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/). Further details can easily be added using *Markdown* and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code. --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ranking and Selection with Covariates for Personalized Decision Making</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/rs-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/rs-c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Affine Processes</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/affine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/affine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Affine processes constitute an important class of continuous time stochastic models that are widely used in finance and econometrics due to their modeling flexibility and computational/analytical tractability. This class of models include affine jump-diffusions (AJDs) and affine point processes (APPs). Examples of AJDs include the Ornstein-Uhlenbeck (OU) process (i.e. the Vasicek model), the square-root diffusion process, (i.e. the Cox-Ingersoll-Ross model), and the Heston stochastic volatility model, all of which are classical models in dynamic asset pricing. On the other hand, examples of APPs include the Hawkes process and its multidimensional extensions, which was applied in credit risk modeling and has lately found important applications in high-frequency trading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arrival Data</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/arrival/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/arrival/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Operational decision making in service systems often depends largely on the characterization of the random fluctuations involved. Exogenous arrivals represent a primary source of uncertainty and their stochastic behavior needs to be modeled carefully. Recent empirical studies demonstrate that the arrival data usually exhibits a dynmacis that is substantially more sophisticated than the Poisson process model (and even the reneal process model), both of which are the underlying assumption of a wide variety of results in the queueing theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization via Sampling</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/rs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/rs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Modern stochastic systems often have a sophisticated structure. Their performance is generally not an analytical function of the decision variables, but a complex surface that can only be evaluated at discrete locations via noisy samples. Since the sampling process is often expensive, we would like to identify the optimal decision with minimal samples. Optimization via sampling is essentially a trade-off between &lt;em&gt;exploitation&lt;/em&gt;, which tends to sample more  at &amp;ldquo;promising&amp;rdquo; areas, and &lt;em&gt;exploration&lt;/em&gt;, which tends to sample more at &amp;ldquo;uncharted&amp;rdquo; areas. Hyperparameter tuning in machine learning is a modernized example of this paradigm of optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rare Event Analysis</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/rare-event/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/project/rare-event/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rare events refer to those that occur with small probabilities but would have substantial impact when they do. Examples include meltdown of a communication network and credit default of a large financial institution. A typical approach to rare event analysis is the large deviations (LD) technique, which characterizes the rare event probability up to the correct logarithmic order of magnitude. To obtain a more accurate estimate, one often resorts to Monte Carlo (MC) simulation. But using the plain vanilla MC to estimate small probabilities requires an enormous number of samples due to the fact that the variance of the MC estimator is orders of magnitude larger than its mean. The LD technique can facilitate to develop importance sampling schemes that reduce the variance of the MC estimator dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poisson Autoregressive Models for Arrival Data</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/par/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/par/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Stochastic Kriging with Markovian Covariances</title>
      <link>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/scalablesk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 18:06:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://xiaoweiz.github.io/publication/scalablesk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
